and Zayn in memory. Zayn hooked up his
own his first solar system today. Give
me Zay. Did anybody see Zayn hooking up
the solar system?
>> How much advanced warning did you have
of that?
>> Zero seconds.
>> How nervous were you?
>> Are you more nervous then now?
>> Good, good, good. Um, but yeah, no
electrical experience at all. Um, it is
kind of idiot proof. Now, as a it is
idiot proof. So, uh, but can I get y'all
to clip and check voltage as these go
down because I can't follow. Now, we
talked about series versus parallel
wiring. We are not going to maximize
this system because I don't feel like
needing 20 panels out. I'm just going to
show you a real life example of how this
works. And we're going to need the
meter.
All right,
got that zing.
And y'all are going to see it happen.
Now, hopefully you're going to get to
see something rating voltage. Now, what
I've done here is just take an MC4
connector and hook it to this one wire.
That way, we can test it all the way
down. I do this all the time. If you
ever ever hook up solar panels, you need
to hook them up one at a time and check
voltage every single time. If not, you
will have clipped 20 panels together and
you'll have a problem at the end and you
don't know where it is. That sucks,
especially if you're on a roof. Ask me
how I know.
I've never read a book on solar. I I'm a
self-taught electrician. I am licensed,
but everything I know has come through
trial and error, mainly error. And uh
I'm passing on all the aggravation
y'all. So first right here. Go Parker.
>> Never disconnect a live solar circuit
like that. [clears throat]
>> I'm wearing flip flops. The ground keeps
it safe. So
now Parker
Zane, you read this out. You're going to
touch it.
Now, look, I'm going to show you a few
things. Go ahead and that one. We have
red and black,
>> and we have two different ones here. You
use this to make sure your orientation
is correct as well. So, what do we read?
>> What do you see? 45 volts.
That is reading 45 volts. What is the
operating voltage?
Vmax, the lower one is 41.96.
So y'all see right now that it is
already floating over that lower
voltage. If you did not figure your clip
voltage, you would have messed up. So if
we wire in series, it's very simple.
>> Who heard the click?
>> Very pertinent. If it does not click,
you have messed up. So, how did we just
wire that series? Negative to positive.
Now, there's little symbols on these,
positive and negative, but y'all can
tell they only go one way. So, if we
wired in series, what would we expect to
see here?
>> 90.2
volts. All right, let's do it again.
>> Hold on. Listen.
Did you hear the click? They have little
stabs in there and these are
weatherproof connectors with grommets.
If you have a loose connection, you will
know. I will show you. So, what should
we see on this side?
>> What you got?
135.4.
180.4
225.7
I want to knock over my la.
>> It's Laqua.
>> No.
>> 270.6.
>> I haven't been shocked yet. Am I doing
that?
316.4.
>> Last one.
>> 361.6.
Any questions on how series adds up
voltage?
Did that look hard, y'all?
The hardest part is mounting these on a
roof. I'm going to go ahead and tell you
there is some trade knowledge required
to install um any roofers out there.
>> Hey, these things go great on metal. I
do not like putting them on shingles. Um
but I love them on metal. Installing the
racks. We're not going to do that today.
That is the hardest part. Trade
knowledge required. I'll show y'all
another day when we ring back up, I
suppose. Now,
what do we have to do with these? Here
you go.
Let's bring that inverter right about
there to the middle along with that
battery.
some negative wires. Now, you should not
be like, you know, tender footing the
live wires. Um, just kind of No, use the
the red one for you.
We're going to come from that side.
Now, what does anybody know how you make
up connectors? Go ahead. Another piece
of wire.
>> Yeah, we got to roll one out.
>> Walk over there without
walk.
Now, this is one of the more aggravating
parts of soldier.
>> Who has ever made up an NC4
communicator?
>> Teach you about Amazon right now.
This is an MC4 connector set. Came off
Amazon. It cost about 30 bucks. This is
the connector crimper that it came with.
I am somewhat of a solar professional.
Um, and I messed up three trying to use
this because it's a piece of
This one came out of my van and it works
fine. But MC4 connectors, there's two
different sizes. Has anybody ever done
one of these before? You have. All
right. You want to give me a hand?
Been a while.
>> Okay. So, y'all want to come close?
There's some detailed stuff here. Get
out one of each.
This would be the trade knowledge.
All righty. Now, if you look at these,
we can see how they go. Mother nature
has taught us how this works. It is Adam
and Eve. Adam
will not work. Okay? Has to go in like
that. The male and the female. All
right? Now, right, easiest way to
remember it. The big one goes in the
little one and the little one's in the
big one. Now, I'm going to tell you, I
have messed up more of these than
anything else. One time you and I put
five wrong in a row. Um, and everybody
will tell you, will you actually install
solar? These little things, you're going
to run out of them. Always get extra.
So, where's that wire?
>> Parker, you want to strip it out for me?
Parker's already got it.
>> You have to cut them off and start over.
Can you get it off?
>> No, you cannot. You mess it up is it
it's trash.
>> Well, I mean, as far as your wire, like
you got your wire measured to a certain
length.
>> Well, I'm going to show you right now.
>> So, we have to hook to that side. And I
believe that is going to be a female
connector. Will you verify for me,
Parker?
>> Yep.
>> All right. And every solar manufacturer,
they don't have a rhyme or reason I've
seen for which one they put on which.
Uh, so I'm going to show you how it
works. We know that this has to go on
that side.
>> Now, when you strip it out, this is the
most important part.
Goes in the big one. Now, you see this?
You do not want the wire to be too long.
Any electricians in here? Y'all see how
that goes up in that hollow tube with
that space? If this has 400 volts coming
through it at 10 amps, what's going to
happen in that little air gap?
>> Arc like hell. So, you have to cut off
right there short. You do not want it
going in there.
It's got to be cut off a little short.
Any electricians in here?
>> These have been blown up several times
with a pair I left in my van.
I still can't use a pair of strippers
cuz they're cheating on.
But now
You take that. You see how that does not
make it into the tube
>> right there? Okay.
>> I made it wrong.
>> Well, see, and that's what happens. The
danger is it worked just fine.